ע"ג Ayin Gimmel 73, and we pick up at the, let’s restart
again at the very bottom of ע"ב עמוד ב'. Ayin Bet Amud
Bet. We just learned the משנה Mishna that spoke about if a
brothers are support- eat on their father's table, but sleep in separate
homes, then they're considered to actually be separate units, and not one
sort of household for עירוב Eruv purposes, each one has to contribute
separately. But it made a distinction that we had also seen before
about whether they are conveying their עירוב Eruv elsewhere, then they’re seen
as separate units. If the עירוב Eruv comes to them, since the
person to whom the עירוב Eruv is placed into, the house person
to whom the עירוב Eruv is placed in doesn’t have to contribute,
somehow because they don’t have to actively contribute, it’s sufficient, then they
are seen as conceptually one household and they do not have to
contribute and they do not have to contribute separately if it is
staying in their house. The גמרא Gemara will get back to that.
The גמרא Gemara said that because it says that they are fundamentally
separate, within this distinction, but fundamentally separate, you see it matters more
where you sleep than where you eat, because it said they’re eating
at their father's table and still they’re defined as separate domiciles. And
the גמרא Gemara said, no, maybe we’re talking about the fact that
they don’t literally eat at their father’s table, but the father sends
them food, but they actually eat separately. And this is going to
be the ongoing question of how do you define primary domicile, which
comes up not only for this, but for issues like lighting חנוכה
Chanukah candles and other types of issues, right, big things, it comes
up all the time with people that are in like dorms in
ישיבה Yeshiva or at college, you know, you eat in a common
room and you sleep in separate rooms, which is your primary domicile?
The משנה Mishna seems to emphasize where you sleep, but the גמרא
Gemara says maybe it’s talking about the fact that you also eat
separately as well. So let’s take a look and pick up from
there.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב יהודה. Amar Rav
Yehuda.
We’ll pick up four lines from the bottom, it’s actually in the
middle of a ברייתא, Baraita, but we’ll pick up. Or
you know what? We’ll do רב יהודה אומר Rav Yehuda Omer actually,
six lines from the bottom, last two words of the line. רב
יהודה אומר אינו אוסר אלא מקום דירה בלבד. Rav Yehuda Omer: Eino
osel ela mekom dira bilvad. The only place that actually creates a
problem for עירוב Eruv is not things like a granary or a
stable, that would not be a problem, the only thing is a
place where somebody actually lives. אמר רב יהודה מעשה בבן נפחא שהיו
לו חמש חצירות באושא, Amar Rav Yehuda: Maaseh beven Nafcha she’hayu lo
chamisha chatzeirot be’Usha, Ben Nafcha had five different courtyards in various places
in אושא, Usha, five different, you know, real estates in five different
courtyards, ובא מעשה לפני חכמים ואמרו אינו אוסר אלא בית דירה בלבד.
uva maaseh lifnei chachamim ve’amru eino osel ela beis dira bilvad. And
the Rabbis said, doesn't matter, his ownership doesn't create a problem for
the people there that want to make an עירוב, Eruv, it’s only
a problem if it's actually a place of domicile. And now we're
going to define what a place of domicile means. So the first
גמרא Gemara says, בית דירה סלקא דעתך? beis dira salkat dach? Literally
you mean a place where people live? It’s not exactly clear what's
bothering the גמרא. Gemara. One of the commentaries explains that it means
that it’s not enough to actually live there, for example, the גמרא
Gemara said that if you have like a gatehouse, that doesn't count
because it’s not fit for living, it doesn’t matter if in practice
somebody happened to be sleeping there or eating there. אלא אימא מקום
דירה. Ella eima mekom dira. Or again, not exactly clear what the
question and the answer is, but the answer somehow is a place,
a place made for, fit for habitation. Now, and now we get
to the key question. So that’s just the issue of what type
of a place has to participate in an עירוב, Eruv, what is
it a place for animals or only a place for human or
you know, a granary, a stable, etc.? רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says
what we've been assuming all along, that it has to be a
place of habitation. And now we're going to define what a place
of habitation means. מאי מקום דירה? Mai mekom dira? רבא אמר, Rava
amar, and this is revisiting, and this is getting back to the
theme that the גמרא Gemara began, top of ע"ג עמוד א', Ayin
Gimmel Amud Aleph, מקום פיתא, mekom pita, a place where you eat
your bread. ושמואל אמר מקום לינה, ve’Shmuel amar: mekom lina, where you
sleep. Now, again, it’s worth noting that there's two potential questions that
this is answering. One is
not that I have to choose between place A and place B,
but can I label this at all a place of habitation? So
I have in your courtyard, I actually sleep in my courtyard, but
in your courtyard is where I always take my lunch. I have
a special house there, I work nearby, I have a special house
in your courtyard and I eat there, and I eat all my
meals there, let's just say, but I sleep somewhere else. Okay, so
the question is, is that considered to be a בית דירה beis
dira that I have to participate in the עירוב? Eruv? Now you
have to choose between A and B, what constitutes a בית דירה
beis dira altogether? What makes it a place where you live? Is
it enough to sleep there? Is it enough to eat there? Do
you need to do both? It could be either. Okay, so that’s
one question. The other question is the issue about sort of when
you have when they’re in competition with one another. Okay, that if
I live, we all share eat in the same place, but we
live separately, are we considered to be sort of one household or
multiple units? And that's the other issue. So again, they could have
the same answer, but it’s worth noting that the first point here
is do you have a domicile in this courtyard? What defines it
as a domicile where you sleep or where you eat? eat or
sleep? And then the other might be if two different types of
things are potentially competing, which one has more weight?
More specifically how regularly, you mean?
Well, right. And so we'll see the גמרא's Gemara going to deal
with a lot of nuances. So רב Rav says it's where you
eat and שמואל Shmuel says it's where you sleep. Yes?
Why would you need an עירוב, Eruv, if you only sleep one
place, but typically you eat somewhere else? You just go and sleep
in some other place.
Well, no, because if the question is that if you don't participate,
if that's considered a house and you don't participate in the עירוב,
Eruv, you're making trouble for everybody else in the חצר, Chatzer, right?
Because everybody has to participate in the
עירוב. Eruv. Yes, so they can just include you, but do you
yourself have to be a participant? For the sake of the courtyard,
not for your sake.
Yes, so they can just include you.
You might not have no need, that's true. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: מיתיבי, Maysivay, I'll ask you on this:
הרועין
והקיצין
והבורגנין ושומרי הפירות, Haroin v'hakayatzin v'haborgnin v'shomrei hapeirows,
so the shepherds and the people that are there when the food
is drying out and the בורגנין Borgnin are also people that sort
of go, you know, sort of nomads, and people that watch fruit.
So these are people that are constantly sort of out there in
the field
during the day with their huts. בזמן שדרכן ללין בעיר, B'zman shedarkan
lalin ba'ir, if they would come back to the city to sleep,
הרי הן כאנשי העיר, Harai hen k'anshei ha'ir, then they're like people
of the city, meaning—and this is a question about back to עירוב
תחומין, Eruv Techumin, right? So notice we're like cutting across categories. So
in regards to עירוב תחומין, Eruv Techumin, where is it that where's
your domicile? And if your domicile's in the city, then the whole
city doesn't count against you, the 2000 אמה Amah starts at the
city's edges. If your domicile is out in the field, then that's
the beginning point, and you don't get the benefit of the whole
city to, you know, to count as four אמות. Amot. So if
you normally sleep in the city, then you're like a then like
you're a city dweller, and the city doesn't count against you and
it's 2000 from the edge of the city. בזמן שדרכן ללין בשדה,
B'zman shedarkan lalin basadeh, if they normally sleep in the field, יש
לו אלפיים לכל רוח, Yesh lo alpain l'chol ruach, you go 2000,
that's not a good thing, it's a bad thing, from where you
normally sleep. Okay, which means that you're obviously going to get a
lot less because you don't get the city to your benefit, although
it'll be a different starting point, it'll be where you normally sleep.
So it seems very clear here, the definition of domicile is where
you sleep. So the גמרא Gemara says, and that's again I'll remind
you the simple sense of our משנה Mishnah as well. So the
גמרא Gemara says: התם אנן סהדי, Hasam anan sahadi, no, you could
claim that it really goes by where you eat. There we testify,
meaning it's self-evident, דאי מטו להו ריפתא התם, D'ee mamtu lehu rifta
hasam, that if they would actually
bring your bread to where you sleep, טפי ניחא להו, Tfai nicha
lehu, you would rather have that. Meaning it could really go by
where you eat. The only thing is that that's when you're sort
of like actively choosing to eat somewhere else, when you've got a
choice. Here the reason I'm eating out in the field is because
I can't I'd rather go home and eat, right? If I worked
next if I worked near my house, I'd go home and eat,
right? I'd go home for lunch. Okay, but you work way out
in the field, you have no choice, so you got to eat
out in the field. But it's not a place you're choosing to
eat, it's a place that you have no other choice but to
eat there. So therefore it becomes very interesting then, the place we
can say that the domicile is defined by the place that you
eat, but now becomes abstracted to be the place that you would
choose to eat had you had, you know, given given all other
things being equal and given total, you know, total choice over the
matter, even if in practice you don't actually eat there. So this
becomes a very slippery category. Let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara will continue in this vein. אמר רב יוסף: Amar Rav Yosef:
לא שמיע לי האי שמעתא, Lo shmi'a li hai shma'ata, you know,
once again רב יוסף Rav Yosef saying, I didn't hear this whole
discussion about
about the debate between whether you go where you eat or where
you sleep. אמר ליה אביי: Amar lei Abaye: את אמרת לן עלה,
At amarta lan alah, so again רב יוסף Rav Yosef had forgotten
things that he taught, and אביי Abaye said: No, no, no, you
told us this issue. והאמרת לן עלה, V'ha'amarta lan alah, and you
told us this debate on the following thing, on our משנה. Mishnah.
האחים שהיו אוכלין על שולחן אביהם וישנים בבתיהם, Ha'achim shehayu ochlin al
shulchan avihem v'yashenin b'vateihem, our משנה, Mishnah, the brothers that eat separate—at
see eat with their father and sleep at home, and in their
individual homes, צריכין עירוב לכל אחד ואחד, Tsrichin eruv l'chol echad v'echad,
they're individual and each one needs an עירוב. Eruv. Okay, ואמרינן לך,
V'amrinan lach, so you said to us, there's a debate here of
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel about whether go
by— ואמרינן V'amrinan means we told you, right?
Yeah, I know, but I'm sorry, yeah, I jumped ahead because I
was going to the punchline. ואמרינן לך שמע מינה מקום לינה גורם,
V'amrinan lach shma mina makom lina gorem, so you see that so
you see that it goes by it goes by where you sleep
because that's the simple sense of the משנה. Mishnah. ואמרת לן, V'amarta
lan, and you said back to us עלה אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב: Alah Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: במקבלי פרס שנו, B'me'kabalei pras
shanu, no, not necessarily. It goes to be maybe it could go
by where you eat and here it doesn't mean that they literally
eat with their father, it means that their father provides their food.
And that's consistent with רב's Rav position that it goes where you
eat. So although the simple sense of the משנה Mishnah is that
it goes where you sleep, רב Rav says it goes where you
eat, and the משנה's Mishnah talking that they don't literally eat with
their father, the father though provides their food. So again, the simple
sense of a couple of the משניות, Mishnayot, our משנה Mishnah says
sleep in separate places, eat with their father, they're considered separate. We
have a משנה Mishnah that speaks about the shepherds that they sleep
in the city and they eat out in
the field. It's true he eats in the field, but he'd rather
be eating at home. So in theory where they would eat is
how you wind up defining it. So now let's see and we've
applied it now to three cases. Case of separate units or one
unit for who has to participate in the עירוב, eruv, the question
of are you considered to have a domicile in the courtyard all
together, and the question about where you start your your שבת Shabbos
where it's considered to be that you begin, you know, that is
your is where you live to where you measure the 2000 אמות.
amot. Yes.
So the reason then so then מאי למימרא שהיו אוכלין על שלחן
אביהם, mai l'meimra shehayu ochlin al shulchan avihem, so we're saying even
in that case where you may have thought that there may be
a little
bit more, that's the that's the way רב Rav would have to
say it, but it's a weak read. תנו רבנן: Tano Rabbanan: מי
שיש לו חמש נשים, Mi sheyesh lo chamesh nashim, somebody who has
married to five women and they all live in different houses in
the courtyard, מקבלות פרס מבעליהן, mekablot pras miba'aleihen, and each and he
sends them food into each one of their
houses, וחמישה עבדים, vechamisha avadim, and five servants, מקבלים פרס מרביהן, mekablim
pras mirabeihen, who also are live in their separate quarters and are
sent and are sent food from their master. So what is the
story? Are they one family unit or multiple family units for the
purpose of עירוב? eruv? So by the way it should be noted
that here it explicitly says that they are sent food, so it's
explicitly the way רב Rav interpreted the משנה, Mishna, they neither sleep
in the same house or eat in the same house, but they
all are of the household in the sense that the one person
the head of the family is the one providing all of all
of the food. So are they one unit or not? So יהודה
בן בתירה מתיר בנשים ואוסר בעבדים Yehuda ben Beseira matir benashim veoser
baavadim says with the women it's okay, meaning presumably they're one family
unit, but not with the slaves, which makes a lot of sense,
you know, you'd assume husband and wife even if they're in different
houses and eat separately one wonders what's going on with the marriage,
but nevertheless we'll consider them to be one family unit for purposes
of עירוב, eruv, whereas the whereas the servants are distinct and therefore
they have to participate separately in the עירוב. eruv. יהודה בן בבא
מתיר בעבדים ואוסר בנשים, Yehuda ben Baba matir baavadim veoser benashim, יהודה
בן בבא Yehuda ben Baba says the opposite, which is a little
bit shocking, so the גמרא Gemara has to explain this. אמר רב
מאי טעמיה דיהודה בן בבא, Amar Rav mai taameh deYehuda ben Baba,
what's his reasoning that he considers the slaves to be one with
the master but not the wives?
דכתיב, Dechtiv, the פסוק pasuk says דדניאל בתרע מלכא, deDaniel bitra malka,
דניאל Daniel was in the gate of the king, so meaning דניאל
Daniel who was the king's attendant slash servant was considered always present
in the same you know you know in the king's castle. So
here saying yep slaves although they are not as it were the
same part of the same family they're always supposed to be in
attendance and therefore conceptually they're always all together whereas I guess wives
in this case are you know their own persons more so even
though it's one you know family unit but they are considered to
be their own persons and if they have own house they are
separate units. תוספות Tosafot by the way points out that it might
be a little play on words or he quotes ר"ח Rach because
תרע tra means gate and the word בבא baba means a gate,
right? And the one who says right בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, בבא
בתרא Bava Basra and this is the one who says this is
רבי יהודה בן בבא. Rabbi Yehuda ben Baba. So he's the play
a little play on words that he's the one that uses this
פסוק pasuk about the gate to say that the servants and the
master are all the same house but wives and husband are separate
units if they live and eat separately. Yes.
Since women have the exact same obligation on עירוב eruv did women
have the same obligation on שבת, Shabbos, why view the women like
the man is the center and women's all sort of satellite? It's
like he's responsible for them but each woman should be responsible for
her own עירוב. eruv.
Right, but the question is if you live in the same house
and it's you and your husband and your five kids and even
if you're all adult you're all responsible but it's one household and
only one has to contribute to the עירוב. eruv.
But physically it's different.
I understand, so the question here is is that
it's not a question of them not being responsible, it's a question
of defining it as one household or not as one household.
If it's one household he's any place
he's
in one house and they're in another house.
There are five possibilities to him. Right. Right. And both but each
woman is has to do her own how can you say he
is in charge what's the difference?
I don't understand, it's a patriarchy,
it's a polygamy, you have a man who is the head of
the household, you have everybody else the children the you know the
slaves the wives all are considered subservient to him, so even if
they're in separate homes, he's the one that continues to be providing
them food, he's still acting as head of the household, so they
might all be considered to be extensions of his one home. That's
a very reasonable thing to assume in a patriarchal context. No no
no not in New Jersey, no no no they're in the same
courtyard. Okay, they all have different homes in the same courtyard. You
know, you might also think about it that you've got this major
estate and you've got your servants' quarters and your wives' quarters, you
know but that's the point because there's a male head of the
household this assumes sort of patriarchal structure that might consider to bring
them all together.
So the woman is
Well
she
is independently obligated, but they might if they're one household, the household
only has to contribute one.
But she—she's not part of the other four households.
I know, but they're all part of the husband's household. They're all
part of the husband's household and that would say that there's one
obligation of עירוב eruv here as one household with five satellites and
only the one household is obligated. That would be the logic.
So it's better to look at her as she's part of only
one household, maybe it's helpful to look at her
as she's part
of his reservoir of power.
Would she have to do בדיקת חמץ? bedikas chometz?
Yes, but there's different or he—he does—that's a good question. He probably
would have to do בדיקת חמץ. bedikas chometz. He probably is, I
mean or נר חנוכה, ner Chanukah, right, נר איש וביתו. ner ish
ubeiso. So that's a you know but yes we're not speaking about
her personal obligation or lack thereof we're speaking about the conceptual unit
of the household. Okay we have to go on. So גמרא Gemara
says like this: תא שמע. ta shma. I'm sorry, so let's take
a look. So by the way that's different than the משנה. mishna.
The משנה mishna said that the sons, the adult sons or presumably
daughters as well, are considered separate units. Even if they eat at
the father's table if you take it literally or certainly if they
just get the food separately, whereas here the wives or servants might
be considered more part of the unit than the adult children. And
here there's a possibility that it's only one household. So גמרא Gemara
says like this: פיתא בן אצל אביו כדתנן. pita ben etzel aviv
ke'asnan. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. A father with the
children like we said in the משנה, mishna, they're separate units. אשה
אצל בעלה ועבד אצל רבו, isha etzel ba'alah ve'eved etzel rabo, wives
or slaves, פלוגתא דרבי יהודה בן בתירה ורבי יהודה בן בבא. plugta
d'Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira ve'Rabbi Yehuda ben Baba. That's a debate. One
of those is going to be a more of a coherent unit,
a tight unit than father and adult children, but it's a debate
which one, the wives or the slaves. תלמיד אצל רבו מהי? talmid
etzel rabo mai? How about a student by his Rebbe? Assuming like
you're boarding for ישיבה, Yeshiva, same type of an idea, you're on
the same courtyard and you know so what's the story? Does that
create a tighter coherent unit than a father and adult children? Because
you can understand that here you know once a child is adult
they more establish their independence whereas here you remain in a relationship
somewhat of dependence, a student and you know and the Rebbe. So...
well let's take a look. We'll see cases like that. תא שמע:
ta shma: דרב בי רבי חייא, d'Rav bei Rabbi Chiya, when Rav
went to the ישיבה Yeshiva of Rabbi Chiya, literally the house of
Rabbi Chiya, אמר אין אנו צריכים לערב, amar ein anu tzerichim le'arev,
he said we the students don't have to make an עירוב eruv
because we're all part of Rabbi Chiya's household. Presumably Rabbi Chiya's household
or ישיבה Yeshiva provided meals for them even in their own units
and nevertheless they were all considered one unit. שאנו סומכין על שולחנו
של רבי חייא, she'anu somchin al xshulchano shel Rabbi Chiya, we rely
on his table, meaning and again presumably even if we don't physically
eat there we're provided by food from there. רבי חייא בי רבי,
Rabbi Chiya bei Rebbi, אמר אין אנו צריכים לערב, amar ein anu
tzerichim le'arev, and when Rabbi Chiya was in Rebbi's ישיבה, Yeshiva, so
this is where Rav learned it from, he said we the students
don't have to make an עירוב. eruv. שאנו סומכין על שולחנו של
רבי, she'anu somchin al shulchano shel Rebbi, we rely on Rebbi. So
very interesting questions of how do you define
a coherence of a unit even when you don't sleep or eat
in the same place, but at least you're connected, there's a central
you know figure that is providing food and providing the—the needs for
everybody else. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. בעי מיניה אביי
מרבא. ba'i minei Abaye mi'Rava. So Abaye asked Rava: חמשה שגבו את
עירובן. chamisha she'gavu es eruvon.
This is really reflecting what we talked yesterday and almost explicit in
the משנה. mishna. Five people collected an עירוב, eruv, כשמוליכין את העירוב
למקום אחר, keshe'molichen es ha'eruv lemakom acher, and now they are going
to contribute their עירוב eruv to let's say another courtyard. But everybody
in this courtyard made an עירוב. eruv. עירוב אחד לכולן או צריכין
עירוב לכל אחד ואחד? eruv echad lekulan o tzerichin eruv lechol echad
ve'echad? Can one person now represent the collective or do they need
individual ones? So אמר ליה עירוב אחד לכולן, amar lei eruv echad
lekulan, one is enough. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute: והא
הכא, veha hacha, the case of the brothers in our משנה, mishna,
דכי גבו דמי? d'chi gavu dami? That it's like they've already made
an עירוב. eruv. How do you know it's like they made an
עירוב? eruv? They're already a unit. What does that mean? Because it
says at the end of the משנה mishna that when the עירוב
eruv comes to them, right, they don't have to do anything, so
they're already some type of a coherent unit. וקתני צריכין עירוב לכל
אחד ואחד? vekatni tzerichin eruv lechol echad ve'echad?
And nevertheless, when they contribute the עירוב eruv outside, right, to the
other members, when they're the contributors not the receivers of the עירוב,
eruv, they're considered separate units. So the same should be, a courtyard
makes an עירוב, eruv, if they receive it it's one thing, but
if they go to contribute an עירוב eruv elsewhere they should be
separate units. That should be just like the brothers and the father.
So גמרא Gemara says no: הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דאיכא דיורין בהדייהו.
hacha bemai askinan kegon de'ika diyarin bahadeihu.
The reason they have to
contribute separately is because there's other people living in the courtyard. And
therefore what? דמיגו דהני אסרי הני נמי אסרי. de'migu dehanei asri hanei
nami asri.
Because these make it forbidden, those make it forbidden. What does that
mean? It means
You have two possible scenarios. One is this is a courtyard, okay,
A and B. In A is just the father and the sons.
Okay, that's one scenario. So they're really all one unit naturally and
if they receive an עירוב Eruv they don't have to contribute. And
maybe even if they brought an עירוב Eruv maybe it would only
be one because they're naturally already, you know, a coherent unit. But
as soon as some stranger comes in the middle, okay,
here's, I don't know, פלוני אלמוני, Ploni Almoni, okay, there's some stranger,
okay,
now whether they're one unit or two units they've got to make
an עירוב. Eruv. Right? An עירוב Eruv is required. So because he
makes it forbidden on them, you know, sort of is the outsider
they can't be considered a tight unit. They're already considered separate units
present here because there's already at least one separate unit. That sort
of creates reality that, you know, now when they make their own
עירוב Eruv they have to contribute, so now also when they go
outside they're also going to have to contribute separately because he just
sort of emphasized, you know, makes that sense of they're like multiple
presences here, not one presence. That seems to be the גמרא's Gemara's
distinction. So the משנה Mishnah that says when they go out that
they have to contribute separately is because they are and that by
the way it helps to understand that if the עירוב Eruv goes
to them, as soon as they're not contributing the עירוב, Eruv, right,
it's there's not like a they're not pointing out the fact that
there are other people present. So if they're receiving the עירוב Eruv
they can consider themselves one unit. They don't have to like actively
acknowledge that there is different units here in this courtyard. But as
soon as they contribute the עירוב Eruv they're sort of acknowledging that
there are different units and therefore they're also distinct units. Okay, so
that's the so so let me just read that again in the
גמרא. Gemara. It says like this. It says,
so oh, but you know, but in the case that רב Rav
was asked, right, let me just do it that way. The case
that רב Rav was asked where you had all of these units
here and they actually made an עירוב, Eruv, they actively made an
עירוב Eruv that combined them. So once you have the reality of
the עירוב Eruv there's nothing that sort of, you know, underscores, points
out that these are separate units. You know, you have an עירוב
Eruv active and everybody everything is fine and dandy. There's nothing that
sort of disrupts that unity. So therefore when you go out one
is enough. But here, although you start like some sense of a
cohesion here, as soon as that unity is disrupted because of the
presence of this person which demands that they acknowledge other people and
that there's other and that they're not just one unit, so therefore
once somebody an outsider comes then they become separate and similarly when
they go to a different courtyard they would have to contribute separately
as well. Okay, unless they've made an עירוב Eruv then it becomes
that case. Yes.
If they're all one unit why do they need an עירוב Eruv
at all?
Down over here?
Ah on the bottom side.
They here they're a unit because they made an עירוב. Eruv.
Because they made an, oh.
This is the case where these are all strangers. Oh okay. I
have a feeling I'm not explaining this well. These are all strangers.
You actively made an עירוב. Eruv. Right. Now you've actively made an
עירוב, Eruv, you're all one unit. There's nothing that breaks you up.
So if you want to contribute to the outside, one is enough.
In our case, okay, if there was no stranger around they there's
no עירוב Eruv being made here, no stranger around, okay, then they
would not need an עירוב. Eruv. That's my question. They don't need
it. They don't need an עירוב. Eruv. But they haven't actively made
one. Okay, as soon as a stranger arrives they have to make
an עירוב. Eruv. So the fact that they have to make it
now essentially breaks them up. It says, hey guys, you're not a
unit. There's other people here. And it makes them individuals. Now again,
if this stranger contributes to the עירוב Eruv then they're not sort
of like actively acknowledging the multiple people in the courtyard. They don't
have to contribute separately. But as soon as they're the ones contributing,
so they're actively acknowledging that there's not just one unit here. And
that's why in this case one is enough and in this case
because there's because there's a stranger they need multiple ones. Okay, yeah.
If they can receive as a unit why can't they give?
So that's what I'm trying to say that when they're receiving they're
not like actively acknowledging, you're just putting bread in my house. I'm
not actively going and participating. I know it's I understand the difficulty.
But somehow that doesn't underscore the fact that there are separate units
here as much as when you actively participate. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says let's read that again. הכא במאי עסקינן דאיכא דדיירין
בהדייהו. Hacha bemai askinan de'ika dedayrin behadayu. There's other people living there.
דמיגו דהני אסרי Demigo dehani asri
because
these strangers make it forbidden, make a problem, you know, and make
it that they're separate units, הני נמי אסרי hani nami asri the
other units of the father and the children become forbid one another
also become separate units. הכי נמי מסתברא Hachi nami mistavra that makes
sense, דתניא אימתי בזמן שמוליכין את. detanya ematai bizman shemolichin et.
When is it that they have to get separately, when they go
out, when they contribute the עירוב. eruv. But if they receive it,
then they're presumably, as I said, somehow not actively acknowledging the fact
that there are multiple units here. Or there's no strangers,
they don't. So you see that what makes them, what breaks them
up is the introduction of strangers. The גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה,
shma mina, that is a good point. It's the introduction of strangers
that creates the problem. But if you have an עירוב eruv in
the courtyard, then they're all one unit and nothing sort of disrupts
that unity, then it's enough to give just one עירוב. eruv. בעי
מיני רב חייא בר אבין מרב ששת. Baei minei Rav Chiya bar
Avin mei-Rav Sheshet. So רב
חייא בר אבין Rav Chiya bar Avin asked רב ששת. Rav Sheshet.
בני בי רב. Bnei bei Rav. So again we're going to
keep guys in ישיבה. yeshiva. Students of the ישיבה, yeshiva, דאכלי נהמא
בבגו, de-achli nahama be-baguei, that they eat, that they eat their bread
out in the like valley there, in some house. That's where they
have the cafeteria. ואתו ובאיתו בבי רב. Ve-atu u-ba-itu be-bei Rav. And
then they come back and they sleep in the בית מדרש, Beis
Medrash, in the ישיבה. yeshiva. כי משחינא להו תחומא מבי רב משחינא
להו או מבגו משחינא להו? Ki mish-china lehu techuma mi-bei Rav mish-china
lehu o mi-baguei mish-china lehu? Where do we start the תחום שבת,
techum Shabbos, where they sleep or where they eat? The classic example
that they dorm in one place and they have a cafeteria in
another place, a חדר אוכל chadar ochel in another place, what's considered
to be their מקום דירה? makom dira? Like the question of רב
ושמואל. Rav u-Shmuel. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, משחינא
מבי רב. mish-china mi-bei Rav. You go from the ישיבה. yeshiva. So
you go where you sleep. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, והרי
נותן עירוב בתוך אלפיים אמה ואתי ובאיתו בביתיה דמשחינא ליה תחומא מעירוביה,
Vaharei noten eruv betoch alpayim ama va-ati u-ba-itu be-veiteih de-mish-china lei techuma
me-eruveih, how could you
say I thought you were going to ask this question. How could
you say you go by where you sleep over where you eat?
Isn't that what all עירוב תחומין eruv techumin is? You put your
food in one place, and you measure from where you put your
food, not from when you go home and you sleep that night?
So therefore that shows that we're defining it more by where you
eat—you don't even really eat there, but at least conceptually, you know,
virtually, rather than your sleep. So why is that different? Why there
do you go from where the food is, not the place you
go home to sleep? One minute. So the גמרא Gemara says, no,
בההוא אנן סהדי ובהא אנן סהדי. Be-hahu anan sa-adei u-ba-hada anan sa-adei.
So now again sort of speaking about the contextual answer. It's not
a black and white sleep versus eat. Like the גמרא Gemara before,
like where would you rather? So it's a question which one place
we are testifying and the other we're testifying. You know, it's self-evident
in each case. בההוא אנן סהדי, Be-hahu anan sa-adei, in the case
of the case of what do you call it, of the of
the עירוב תחום, eruv techum, it's self-evident, דמיטר ליה התם ניחא ליה.
De-miter lei hatam nicha lei.
Since anyway you want to travel to the next city for, you
know, that's why you're putting your תחום, techum, because you want to
go in let's say north, more north on שבת, Shabbos, you would
prefer to have a house where your עירוב eruv is. It would
save you having to go back and forth. Right, you went ahead
and you put your עירוב eruv at the northernmost extremity of the
תחום. techum. So now you have to schlep back home, and then
tomorrow morning you're going to have to schlep out to the עירוב
eruv and go another two thousand אמה. ama. So presumably, you would
actually rather this be the place if you had a house here
you'd rather start here. So again you want to go in the
direction you put the עירוב. eruv. So you'd rather get a head
start and start where not necessarily, yeah, all your friends back there,
it's worth the schlep back to the city to spend Friday night
with all your friends, and then but okay, that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. Okay, so in theory you'd rather do it all out
there. ובהא, U-va-hada,
and in the case of the חדר אוכל chadar ochel and the
בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, אנן סהדי, anan sa-adei, דמייתו לריפתא לבי רב
ניחא להו. de-maisu le-rifta le-bei Rav nicha lehu.
They'd rather eat where they're sleeping. They'd just have to, you know,
okay, they made the חדר אוכל chadar ochel somewhere else but they'd
rather eat where they're sleeping. So again the גמרא Gemara sort of
finesses the question of where you eat versus where you sleep by
sort of saying that we can sort of raise it up contextually
in various cases. So, you know, what person you'd say you always
go by where you eat, but sometimes they'll say, in theory you'd
rather be eating here. You always go by where you sleep, but
even if you didn't sleep here I could say in theory you'd
rather be sleeping here and therefore that case is covered. So it's
hard to pin down one rule regarding these issues. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: ניחא ליה טפי. nicha lei tavei. בעי
רמי בר חמא מרב חסדא. Baei Rami bar Chama mei-Rav Chisda. רמי
בר חמא Rami bar Chama asked רב חסדא. Rav Chisda.
אב ובנו, הרב ותלמידו. Av u-veno, ha-Rav ve-talmido. So this seems very
similar to the previous question. You have a father and his children,
or the רב Rav and students. לרבים דמו או כיחידים דמו? Le-rabim
damu o ke-yechidim damu? Are they like separate units or an individual
unit? Now it sounds like that's what we've all been discussing. So
according to רש"י Rashi it really is a bit of a rehash
about what we've been discussing,
and תוספות Tosafot sort of says maybe the question has to do
again with this issue about maybe before we were talking about eating
at the same table, now we're talking about eating at different tables.
Anyway, it's more or less a rehash of what we're discussing.
Why don't they include the man with the five wives in this
list?
I don't know because that's a good question. Maybe these were the
ones I don't know. These are at least two extreme. The man
with the children was clear in the משנה Mishnah that they're separate
units, more than the other cases, and the רב Rav with the
students everybody seemed to agree it was one unit. So maybe it
takes doing the two and the wives and the slaves were debated,
but yet presumably they'd be subject to the same question. Are they
like many or are they like single? So what is that question?
דאמרו: Damru: צריכים עירוב או אין צריכים עירוב? Tsrichim eruv o ein
tsrichim eruv? First of all, do they need an עירוב eruv or
not? Which could mean, which means like if they're the only members
of a courtyard, do they need an עירוב? eruv? We've already said
no, but again he's re-asking this. מהו שלן הניתר בלחי וקורה או
אינו ניתר בלחי וקורה? Mahu shelan hanitar belechi vekorah o einu nitar
belechi vekorah? How about if they have a מבוי? mavoi? The general
rule we're going to see is there's this idea that a מבוי
mavoi doesn't need a full-force wall. You've got your מבוי mavoi like
this, you've got the courtyards opening up into it, and it's a
dead-end מבוי, mavoi, and all you have to do here is a
לחי lechi or קורה. korah. It doesn't need a full-force wall. But
they only allowed that when it was defined as a מבוי. mavoi.
What defines it as a מבוי? mavoi? That you have חצרין, chatzerin,
you have more than one חצר, chatzer, and each חצר chatzer has
at least, so you have two חצרין chatzerin and two בתים batim
in each חצר. chatzer. So you need at least two חצרין chatzerin
and two בתים batim to be defined as a מבוי. mavoi. Otherwise
we're going to require a real-force wall. But let's say one of
the courtyards is all a ישיבה, yeshiva, a ישיבה yeshiva and its
dormitory, or all a father and his adult children in separate homes.
Is this two בתים batim or one בית? bayit? And here actually,
if it's one בית bayit it's a חומרא chumra because then you
don't have an official courtyard because you only have one בית bayit
in this חצר, chatzer, and therefore you need at least two חצרין
chatzerin each one with two בתים batim and therefore the לחי lechi
or the קורה korah will not work. מהו היתרא בצורת הפתח? mahu
hitra betzurat hapetach? What?
You have to do it בצורת הפתח betzurat hapetach או אינו ניתר
בלחי וקורה. o einu nitar belechi vekorah. Now I should say רש״י
Rashi actually understands the question of individuals or single not as an
abstract question but as another application. And his application is, I know
you all love this case, here's your street, I'm teasing because we've
had this before, here's your courtyard A and your courtyard B. And
because B has to go through A, if B hasn't made an
עירוב, eruv, then A's got a problem. They have to make an
עירוב eruv together in order or else they're considered present in A.
So if you have here the ישיבה yeshiva or the father with
the children, is that like a group of people that haven't made
an עירוב eruv that creates a problem on A, or is it
like one person is living there who does not create a problem
on A? All these various
questions. So אמר ליה, Amar lei, which gets back to our משנה.
Mishnah. Our משנה Mishnah basically says sometimes it's one unit, sometimes it's
multiple, depending on which way they're contributing the עירוב. eruv. So here
it seems like he's asking the question bottom line what's their fundamental
definition. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him, תניתוה. Tanituha.
We taught it: אב ובנו, הרב ותלמידו. Av uveno, harav vetalmido. So
this is a ברייתא braita which sort of re-emphasizes what we just
said a minute ago: בזמן שאין עמהם דיורין, Bizman she’ein imahem diyurin,
if there's nobody else in the courtyard, הרי הן כיחידים, harei hen
kiyachidim, then they're like individuals. Remember we just said it a minute
ago that it's only the presence of strangers or maybe the active
participating in another person in the in another עירוב eruv that defines
them as a separate unit. But if there's no strangers there, then
they're defined as a coherent unit. הרי הן כיחידים harei hen kiyachidim
ואין צריכים לערב. ve’ein tsrichim l’arev. They don't have to make their
own עירוב. eruv. But that being said, ומבוי שלהן ניתר בלחי וקורה,
Umavoi shelahen nitar belechi vekorah, we have both leniencies: although they are
one unit and they don't have to make their own עירוב eruv
and they don't create problems for B, in this case of the
courtyards, they're enough of a separate unit that this is considered a
legitimate חצר chatzer and therefore you have the leniency of a לחי
lechi or a קורה. korah. So basically means there's no fixed answer;
they basically have the coherence of one unit but to some degree
they're separate. And this is what we've seen in the משנה: Mishnah:
when you introduce outside people, then they actually become separate. So here
too, they're basically one unit, but they're separate enough that they have
the leniency of the לחי lechi or קורה. korah. So the answer
is, it depends. Let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishnah.
What? למעשה? Lema’aseh? What do we say? למעשה, Lema’aseh,
we'll worry about that next time we have a courtyard that has
all people. The real big question
is about מקום לינה makom linah or מקום פיתא makom pita and
that's majorly debated in the פוסקים poskim how to deal with that,
comes up all the time with חנוכה Chanukah questions. Let's take a
look. So it says like this: חמש חצרות פתוחות זו לזו ופתוחות
למבוי. Chamesh chatzerot petuchot zu lazu upetuchot lemavoi. So this is going
to sound familiar, not the the issue that goes on here. You
have five חצרות chatzerot that are open to one another and open
into the street. You have a little picture in the lower right-hand
corner. עירבו בחצרות ולא נשתתפו במבוי, מותרים בחצרות ואסורים במבוי. Eirvu bachatzarot
velo nishtatfu bemavoi, mutarim bachatzarot ve’asurim bemavoi.
So this is again the question of can you use the שיתופי
מבואות shitufay meva’ot in place of the עירוב חצרות eruv chatzerot and
vice versa. So you have all of these different חצרות chatzerot and
they're all open up into the street. Okay,
so if they all because they open into one another you can
make an עירוב eruv amongst the חצרות chatzerot which makes sense which
makes them one coherent unit, right? Okay, if you did that, if
you did that, then is there still a need to do a
שיתוף מבוי? shituf mavoy? Or if you did a שיתוף מבוי shituf
mavoy maybe that already defines them as unified and maybe then they
can carry like from one to the other because the מבוי mavoy
שיתוף shituf is what makes them one coherent unit? So this is
what we've seen before the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
the חכמים, Chachamim, can a שיתוף shituf or an עירוב eruv substitute
for one another? So we, well before we quoted it as a
ברייתא, braita, here it's a משנה. mishna. חמישה, Chamisha,
let's do it again, חמישה חצרות פתוחות זו לזו ופתוחות למבוי. chamisha
chatzerot ptuchot zu lezu u'ptuchot le'mavoy. עירבו בחצרות, Ervu b'chatzerot,
if you made an עירוב eruv of the court yards, so now
all the courtyards are one coherent unit, ולא נשתתפו במבוי, velo nishtatfu
b'mavoy, and you didn't do a שיתוף מבוי, shituf mavoy, מותרים בחצרות
ואסורים במבוי, mutarin b'chatzerot v'asurin b'mavoy, the מבוי mavoy is still off
limits, okay. And you could understand that because conceptually you've made this
a unit but it doesn't relate to the street. Now you could
say but if we're one person, one unit, then there's not multiple,
there's not competition in the street, the street is all... but nevertheless
you still need, you haven't included that, that's a separate domain. ואם
נשתתפו במבוי מותרים כאן וכאן. Ve'im nishtatfu b'mavoy mutarin kan v'kan.
However, if you made a שיתוף shituf in the מבוי mavoy then
everybody is permissible. And you also understand that because they're all sort
of coming together in the street but they're as it were coming
out of their courtyards, right? And sort of showing that they're all
coherent, you know, sharing the space of the street. So unifying in
the street also unifies the courtyards together and the שיתוף shituf can
count, you know, and then you can go from one to the
other. Does that depend on how you made it? Now that's what
the משנה mishna says. The משנה mishna says that the מבוי mavoy
brings together the courtyards but the courtyards doesn't bring together the מבוי.
mavoy. The גמרא Gemara is going to say, doesn't understand the asymmetry,
and the גמרא Gemara is going to say the משנה mishna is
contradictory. Either one works instead of the other or one doesn't work
instead of the other. But I have to tell you personally to
me it makes a lot of sense because this does not relate
to the reality of the מבוי mavoy but this, all the courtyards
are coming together in the מבוי, mavoy, brings together the courtyards and
the מבוי. mavoy. But so that's the asymmetry in the משנה mishna
although the גמרא Gemara will not understand, will not believe, you know,
that that, that you can have that asymmetry, yes.
That's why you said before it really depends on how you did
it, with the פת pat versus the יין?
yayin? Yeah, yeah, yeah, so the גמרא Gemara isn't getting into that
now but yes, it might depend on that. Now עירבו בחצרות ונשתתפו
במבוי, eirvu b'chatzerot v'nishtatfu b'mavoy,
now let's say you did both, ושכח אחד מבני חצר ולא עירב,
v'shachach echad mibnei chatzer v'lo eirav, but one person of the חצר
chatzer forgot to do the עירוב, eruv, so effectively what does that
become? If one person forgot to do the עירוב, eruv, then it
becomes a case where you had the שיתוף shituf but you didn't
have the עירוב, eruv, and we just said that that case you're
okay. מותרים כאן וכאן. Mutarin kan v'kan. מבני מבוי ולא נשתתף, Mibnei
mavoy velo nishtatef, if one courtyard forgot to participate in the מבוי,
mavoy, then that's a case of having an עירוב eruv without a
שיתוף. shituf. So מותרים בחצרות ואסורים במבוי, mutarin b'chatzerot v'asurin b'mavoy, it's
the exact same הלכה, halacha, okay. So the שיתוף, shituf, the שיתוף
shituf
substitutes for the עירוב eruv but not the reverse. שהמבוי לחצר כחצר
לבתים, She'hamavoy l'chatzer k'chatzer l'batim, and now sort of pointing out
that
the relationship of the מבוי mavoy to the courtyards is similar to
the relationship of the courtyard to the houses. And if one person
sits out of the שיתוף shituf the whole שיתוף shituf doesn't take
place and if one house sits out of the עירוב eruv the
עירוב eruv doesn't take place. Okay. So the basic point here being
that a שיתוף shituf can substitute for an עירוב eruv but not
vice-versa. As I said the גמרא Gemara does not like this asymmetry.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. גמרא Gemara says like
this: מני? Mani? So the first part which said that the עירוב
eruv doesn't substitute for the שיתוף shituf who is that? That's רבי
מאיר היא, Rabbi Meir hi, דאמר בעינן עירוב ובעינן שיתוף, d'amar ba'inan
eiruv u'ba'inan shituf, you need both. So if you forgot the עירוב
eruv if you forgot the שיתוף shituf the עירוב eruv doesn't help
you. אימא מציעתא, Eima metziata, how about the middle case? ואם נשתתפו
במבוי מותרים כאן וכאן, Ve'im nishtatfu b'mavoy mutarin kan v'kan, that the
שיתוף shituf can help you even if you don't have an עירוב.
eruv. אתאן לרבנן, Atan l'rabbanan, that's going like the רבנן, Rabbanan, דאמרי
בחדא סגיא, d'amri b'chada sagi, one is enough. Okay, so it's quite
fascinating, right? The גמרא Gemara says it's either one is enough or
you always need two. It doesn't want to accept the possibility that
there's an asymmetry and that the שיתוף shituf works better than the
עירוב. eruv. So how do you make sense of this משנה? mishna?
So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult.
ואי נשתתפו נמי קאמר. Ve'i nishtatfu nami ka'amar. So when it says
that if you did the שיתוף shituf then it works for both,
it doesn't mean only the שיתוף. shituf. It means if you also
did the שיתוף, shituf, which of course makes it almost a nonsensical
statement, right? If you did the עירוב eruv it doesn't work for
both, but if you did the עירוב eruv and the שיתוף, shituf,
it does work for both. Like okay of course. אימא סיפא, Eima
seifa, so we'll revise it, let's look at the end. עירבו בחצרות
ונשתתפו במבוי ושכח אחד מבני חצר ולא עירב מותרים כאן וכאן. Eirvu
b'chatzerot v'nishtatfu b'mavoy v'shachach echad mibnei chatzer v'lo eirav mutarin kan v'kan.
So if one person did not do the
עירוב, eruv, right, one person did not do the עירוב. eruv. then
you're okay because the מבוי mavoi backs you up. The שיתוף מבוי
shitof mavoi works, backs you up. So the גמרא gemara says היכי
דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אי דלא ביטיל, ei delo bitel,
אמאי מותרים? amai mutarim?
If you didn't do a ביטול bittel assuming, like you're assuming what
the גמרא gemara says, you're assuming that it is רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and that it doesn't back you up. So then how come
here when you forgot to do the עירוב eiruv is everything okay?
אלא פשיטא, ella pshita, it must be that if you're assuming רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and one thing doesn't stand in and you forgot
to do the עירוב eiruv and it's מותר, mutar, so why does
it work?
אלא פשיטא דביטיל, ella pshita debatiel, you did ביטול. bittel. אימא סיפא,
ayma seifa, now let's look at the last case. שכח אחד מבני
מבוי ולא נשתתפו, shachach echad mibnei mavoi velo nishtatfu, if one of
the people at the מבוי mavoi forgot, מותר בחצרות ואסור במבוי. mutar
bachatezeros ve'asur bamavoi.
You can use the courtyards but not the מבוי. mavoi. So the
גמרא gemara says why? ואי דביטיל אמאי אסור במבוי, ve'i debatiel amai
asur bamavoi, but if you did ביטול, bittel, why is it אסור
asur in the מבוי? mavoi? You did ביטול, bittel, that should work.
Okay, so basically the גמרא, gemara, it's a little complicated, but the
גמרא gemara is just pointing out that that's clearly not פשט pshat
in the משנה. mishna. The משנה mishna is very clearly saying that,
you know, the שיתוף shitof works instead of the עירוב eiruv but
not vice versa. The גמרא gemara wants to say it's either all
or nothing. So it's trying to say it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and that really one does not substitute. But if one doesn't substitute,
why at the end of the משנה mishna do we find that
sometimes it works? Oh, that's 'cause you did ביטול. bittel. But if
you did ביטול, bittel, then it should always work. Again, how do
you explain this asymmetry? So the גמרא gemara says וכי תימא קסבר
רבי מאיר אין ביטול רשות במבוי, vechi tayma kasavar Rabbi Meir ein
bittel reshus bamavoi, maybe it's a completely different issue. That maybe the
reason that it doesn't work at the end of the משנה mishna
when you forgot to do the שיתוף shitof is because maybe you
can't do ביטול bittel by a מבוי. mavoi. Maybe you can only
do ביטול bittel by a חצר. chatzer. But that's not true. והתניא
שהרי ביטלו לכם רשות דברי רבי מאיר. vehatanya sheharei bitelu lachem reshus
divrei Rabbi Meir. If you remember when we were talking about the
צדוקי, Tzadoki, we had a case that somebody forgot to participate in
a מבוי mavoi or not forgot, the צדוקי Tzadoki didn't participate in
the מבוי mavoi and it worked because of ביטול. bittel. So anyway,
ביטול bittel can work whether in a חצר, chatzer, whether in a
מבוי. mavoi. So if you say it's all רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
you haven't explained the asymmetry of why when you forget the עירוב
eiruv you're still okay and when you forget the מבוי mavoi you're
not good. And it can't be because you did ביטול bittel because
then you should always be okay. אלא פשיטא דלא ביטיל. ella pshita
delo batiel. It must be that since it says if you forget
the שיתוף shitof you've got a problem, that we're assuming ביטול bittel
is not
present. ומדסיפא דלא ביטיל, umedeseifa delo batiel, since the last case when
you didn't do the שיתוף shitof and you have a problem is
that there was no ביטול, bittel, רישא נמי דלא ביטיל. reisha nami
delo batiel. So the whole thing is no ביטול. bittel. So we're
back to our question. Our question is why when you sit out
the שיתוף shitof you have a problem, you can't use the מבוי,
mavoi, and when you sit out the עירוב eiruv you're okay. Now
again, the obvious answer is that it's asymmetrical. Joining in the שיתוף
shitof works better than joining in the עירוב, eiruv, you know, to
include the מבוי. mavoi. But the גמרא gemara does not want to
say that. The גמרא gemara says רישא וסיפא רבי מאיר מציעתא רבנן?
reisha veseifa Rabbi Meir metziata Rabbanan? So again, the beginning and the
end is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. It says that one doesn't back
it up. The middle that says
the שיתוף shitof backs up, that's going like the Rabbis. How do
you make a consensus out of this? The גמרא gemara says כולה
רבי מאיר. kulla Rabbi Meir. No, no, no, let's try again. It's
all רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. וטעמא מאי, vetaama mai, here's I'm going
to explain to you why it's
different. וטעמא מאי אמר רבי מאיר בעינן עירוב ובעינן שיתוף, vetaama mai
amar Rabbi Meir be'inan eiruv ube'inan shitof, why does רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir say you always need both? שלא לשכח תורת עירוב מן התינוקות,
shelo lishakeach toras eiruv min hatinokos, 'cause in principle really one could
substitute. But we don't want to forget that you have the both
הלכות halachas here because sometimes you'll have one without the other. והכא
כיון דרובא עירבו, vehacha keivan deruba yerbu, so the last case, why
is it that the שיתוף shitof is a backup? Because what happened?
Everybody made an עירוב eiruv and in one courtyard one guy forgot
to contribute. So since it's only because of that, so כיון דרובא
עירבו לא משתכחא, keivan deruba yerbu lo mishtakcha, it's not going to
be forgotten, which is a very bizarre הלכה. halacha. It's sort of
like the types of questions that Michael asks, like let's just assess
every case as it comes up. Okay, so basically what it's saying
is really this is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, so an עירוב eiruv
doesn't substitute for a שיתוף shitof and a שיתוף shitof doesn't substitute
for an עירוב, eiruv, okay, and the first case in the משנה
mishna when it said שיתוף shitof worked really meant שיתוף shitof plus
עירוב eiruv works. So what about the case where one of these
guys forgot and therefore this עירוב eiruv didn't take place and we're
saying that it's still okay because you did the שיתוף? shitof? So
we're saying, look, the whole reason he doesn't like this to work
for this or vice versa is he doesn't want the whole principle
that there are two things going on forgotten here. Here everybody actively
did an עירוב eiruv and everybody actively did a שיתוף, shitof, and
just one guy forgot, so we'll let that case go. Okay, it's
a very weak answer. I mean, and let's say two people forgot?
Right, and let's say what, one out of how many? And whatever.
It's a very weak answer, and but at least shows that רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir in principle agrees with the רבנן. Rabbanan. The real
פשט pshat of the משנה mishna seems to be like I said,
there's an asymmetry. שיתוף shitof more brings everybody together than the עירוב,
eiruv, which more keeps the מבוי, mavoi, the street, out of the
picture. But the גמרא gemara for some reason does not even consider
that. Let's take a look. אמר רב יהודה... Amar Rav Yehuda... Now
we're going to go on a different tack. רב *Rav* לא תני
*lo tani* פתוחה זו לזו *ptucha zu lezu*. רב *Rav* does not
have the text in the משנה *Mishnah* that they open one to
another, the courtyard. וכן אמר רב כהנא *V'chein amar Rav Kahana* רב
לא תני פתוחה זו לזו *Rav lo tani ptucha zu lezu*. His
case was not that they were open one to the other. Now
you could have just said: okay, so it's telling you a different
הלכה *halacha*. And how do you make an עירוב eruv *eruv* together
could have been the question. Well that might have been, so the
עירוב eruv. *eruv* means they made individual עירובין *eruvin*, which would also
explain why the עירוב eruv, *eruv* doesn't substitute for the שיתוף shituf.
*shituf*, because they're individual units and therefore they're not brought together. The
only thing that brings them together is the שיתוף shituf. *shituf*. It
actually solves the רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* problem, right? The גמרא's Gemara
*Gemara's* problem is: why does the שיתוף shituf *shituf* work and not
the עירוב eruv *eruv*? Well, if you say that the עירוב eruv.
*eruv* does not mean they were עירוב eruv. *eruv* together but they
were individual units that were עירוב eruv, *eruv*, so obviously that's not
going to help you unify them for the street. But if the
street unifies them, then it also helps unify them, then the שיתוף
shituf. *shituf* can be a substitute to that would seem to be
why רב *Rav* takes out that line, it solves this problem. But
again the גמרא *Gemara*
is
going to go on a different, it's not the גמרא *Gemara* is
going to go on a different tack. Let's see what the גמרא
*Gemara* says. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף *Amar lei Abaye l'Rav Yosef*.
אביי *Abaye* said to רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*. מאי טעמא דלא תני
פתוחה זו לזו *Mai ta'ama d'lo tani ptucha zu lezu*? Why did
he reject the גירסא *girsa* that they open one to the other?
So as I said, it could have been because that deals with
the גמרא's *Gemara's* problem: why the שיתוף *shituf* works better than the
עירוב eruv, *eruv*. But the גמרא's *Gemara's* going to say a different
reason, that he actually thinks that if they're open one to another
it creates more problems. קסבר כל שיתוף שאין מכניסו ומוציאו דרך פתחים
במבוי לא שמיה שיתוף *Kasvar kol shituf she'ein machniso umotzio derech ptachim
bamavoy lo shmeh shituf*. Any שיתוף *shituf* that you don't have to
go in and out of the street to make it happen, or
that you don't actively do it, is not a שיתוף *shituf*, which
means what? You have this case again. Okay, you've got...
right,
you've got this case. Now if there were no, if the courtyards
were not open one to another and you have to go collect
the bread or the wine to make your שיתוף *shituf*, what are
you going to do? So here you are, you start here, you're
going to get some wine here, then you're going to walk here,
get this guy to contribute, blah blah blah, get this guy to
contribute and maybe deposit it here. So in the process of collecting
your עירוב eruv *eruv*, it's very fascinating that the גמרא *Gemara* looks
at this, how this act
unifies them and makes them coherent. You are going to each of
the courtyards through the street, and therefore it's seen as you're unifying
them to create a שיתוף *shituf* and the street becomes part of
the unit. But if you had like this and you could go
like this, you could make the
שיתוף *shituf* without ever going into the street. And therefore that would
not be a good שיתוף *shituf*. So it's fascinating, it's not just
the fact that everybody contributed, it's the way in which you bring
them all together. So since if they opened one to another, it
would be possible that you would never go in the street and
then it wouldn't be good. We're not going to allow you in
this case to make a שיתוף *shituf* because you might do it
this way and that won't be a שיתוף *shituf*.
You're telling them
you're doing it for a שיתוף *shituf*? Yeah, exactly. So that's this
גמרא *Gemara* here. The גמרא's *Gemara's* going to reject it. But it's
quite fascinating that at this stage the גמרא *Gemara* assumes that in
order for the שיתוף *shituf* to work, you have to actively go
in and out of the courtyards and into the streets. So when
they open one to another, it should be a problem and we
won't allow it. Yes?
The language they say here: לא שמיה שיתוף *lav shmeh shituf*. That's
kind of...
Right, it's not called a שיתוף *shituf*. So yeah, it's true, maybe
it also indicates that the problem is the reality of unifying them.
So now the גמרא's *Gemara's* going to have a lot of questions
on this. Don't worry, we'll reject it. איתיבי *Eitivi*.
בעל הבית שהיה
שותף לשכנו ולזה ביין ולזה ביין *Ba'al habayit shehayah shutaf lishcheino v'lazeh
b'yayin v'lazeh b'yayin*. Remember the משנה *Mishnah* that you happen to be
in business with your friend and everybody in the barrel of wine
and that was a שיתוף *shituf* because it was wine. So אין
צריכים לערב *ein tzerichim l'arev*. So presumably
that means that we were business partners in any random way. גמרא
*Gemara* says: לא התם דאפקי ועיילי *lo hatam d'afkei v'ayeilei*. There too
when you were going into business, you took your barrel in and
out of the courtyards through the street to everybody and everybody contributed
their wine. Okay, again a quite a very
hard to believe אוקימתא *ukimta*. Okay, let's try again. כיצד משתתפין במבוי
*Keitzad mishtatfin bamavoy*. It says how do you do a שיתוף *shituf*
in a מבוי mavoi? *mavoy* and it basically says that one person
can pick up the loaf of bread for everybody. So how can
one person pick up the loaf of bread for everyone? Don't you
have to walk in and out of the courtyards and go through
the street? So the גמרא *Gemara* says: התם נמי דאפקי ועיילי *hatam
nami d'afkei v'ayeilei*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says there too. So it's
pretty bizarre. You take your loaf of bread but first you walk
in and out of the courtyards after you do the transfer of
ownership. So it's again this bizarre idea that it's the walking that
is bringing it all together. מתקיף לה רבה בר בר חנה *Matkif
lah Rabba bar bar Chana*. אלא מעתה *Ela me'ata*, if that's true,
הקנה לו פת בסלו הכי נמי דלא הוי שיתוף *hikneh lo pat
b'salo hachi nami d'lo havei shituf*? So do you mean to tell
me, which is pretty much similar to what we just said before,
that if I just transfer ownership of a loaf of bread in
my basket to everybody in the courtyard that it doesn't work? וכי
תימא הכי נמי *V'chi teima hachi nami*, and if you say yes,
that is true, you have to get active participation and go through
the street. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב בני חבורה שהיו מסובים *D'amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav bnei chaburah shehayu mesubin*. People who were all
having a nice meal. all together, reclining together having a meal on
Friday, וקדש עליהם היום and poof it became Shabbos, nobody was looking
at the clock, הפת שעל השולחן hapat she'al hashulchan סומכין עליה משום
עירוב somchin aleha mishum eruv ואמרי לה משום שיתוף ve'amre lah mishum
shituf they can use the bread that they were all sharing together
to be the bread of עירוב eruv and the bread of שיתוף.
Interestingly, תוספות Tosafos points out, even if it's all my bread. This
raises interesting halachic questions. When I invite you to my house and
I say, "here, have an apple," am I transferring the ownership of
the apple to you? Presumably not, I'm letting you eat my apple.
Okay. So what?
Why would you give
it to me as mine? No, not necessarily. Not necessarily. If you
said thank you and you walked out, I'd say, "whoa, wait a
minute, I was only giving it to you to eat here in
the house," you'd have to give it back to me, right? You'd
say, "oh, you already מקנה makne it to me." No, I'm letting
you eat my apple. So, similarly, תוספות Tosafos says, you're all eating
bread at my house, even though it's still my bread, because we're
all sharing the bread, that substitutes for an עירוב. eruv, Even though
it wasn't done consciously for an עירוב, like the case of going
into business with the wine. Okay, so that's what the ברייתא braisa
is teaching. And some say it can even substitute for a שיתוף.
So what's the debate? דאמר רבה לא פליגי. de'amar Rabbah lo peligi.
It's not... they're not really debating. כאן במסובין בבית, kan bemesubim bevayis,
if you're having your meal in a house, so the עירוב is
deposited in the house, so it can substitute for an עירוב. וכאן
במסובין בחצר, vekan bemesubim bechatzer, if you're having... it's a nice day
outside and you're having your meal in the חצר. chatzer. So where
do you deposit the שיתוף of the מבוי? mavoi In the חצר.
chatzer. So it really can substitute for either. If it's in the
house, it substitutes for the עירוב. If it's in the חצר, chatzer,
it substitutes for the שיתוף. But what do you see? It's very
clear that you did not go in and out of each courtyard
through the street to make this happen. Okay, so it is a
fascinating idea that if the purpose is to unify, that you have
to do an actively collecting of it and bringing all the properties
and the street together. I like the idea; it talks about the
way in which you unify. But at the end of the day,
it's enough just to transfer ownership or to have everybody like eat
off of my bread. So therefore, that cannot be what's going on
here. So the גמרא rejects it. You're right. Forget that whole approach.
So the Rav says, אלא טעמא דרב... ella taama deRav... So what's
Rav's reason? דקסבר אין מבוי ניתר בלחי וקורה עד שיהיו בתים וחצרות
פתוחים לתוכו. dekasavar ein mavoi nitar belechi vekora ad sheye'u batim vechatzeros
pesuchim letocho. Similar thing we said before. In this case, because they
could make one עירוב, okay, and maybe they are making one עירוב,
they really become considered one חצר. chatzer. And in order for it
to be a מבוי that you can use a לחי lechi or
קורה, kora, you need two חצרות. chatzeros. Okay, so quite a... fascinating
that somehow when it gets better, there's a way in which it
gets worse. So Rav doesn't like this case. You're allowed to make
an עירוב here, but as soon as you make an עירוב here,
you've turned it into one courtyard, and then a לחי lechi or
קורה kora would not be a good...
unless of course you had other courtyards here, other courtyards that
stuck out of the עירוב, okay. But if you tried to do...
but anyway, but that is the issue and not the other one.
We'll continue and see more about this tomorrow.